[{"question":"<p>Increase in the number of people living below the poverty line in Africa is particularly because<\/p>","options":["The largest proportion of Africa's populations are unemployed","Of the prevalence of corruption","Of the problem of insecurity scaring away investors","A vast majority of its populants have chosen to be unproductive"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The First and Second World Wars were between ... respectively<\/p>","options":["1939-1945, 1914-1918","1914-1918, 1939-1945","1914-1919, 1932-1942","1914-1919, 1939-1945"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The main motive behind imperialism has been aforetime categorised as primarily<\/p>","options":["to colonise less developed states","the socio-economic transformation agenda for Africa","to expand socio-cultural territories of the Western powers","being to obtain and control a supply of raw materials for industries"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The most immediate reason for the declaration, by Ojukwu, of Eastern Nigeria as an independent State of Biafra was that<\/p>","options":["The Gowon-led coup strictly targeted the Igbos","The wanted the freedom for the Igbos at all cost","Of the creation of twelve States by Gowon to dismantle any secessionist agenda","corruption and oppression was too prevalent in Nigeria"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Igbo&#39;s active resistance to the British Colonial rule is particularly because of the<\/p>","options":["impression that the British officials favoured the Northerners","maladministration of the British Indirect rule Policy","regressive taxation of their society","egalitarian nature of their society"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Colony and Protectorate of Lagos and the Protectorate of Southern Nigeria were merged in ... to form<\/p>","options":["1906, Colony and Protectorate of Southern Nigeria","1901, Colony and Protectorate of Southern Nigeria","1906, Lagos Colony and Southern Nigeria Protectorate","1901, Colony and Protectorate of Nigeria"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The major administrative change made immediately after the 1914 Amalgamation was the?<\/p>","options":["introduction of a direct taxation system","creation of districts for political convenience","imposition of warrant chiefs in the Eastern Region","division of Nigeria into provinces"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The particular incident that led to Macaulay&#39;s imprisonment, twice, by the colonial power was<\/p>","options":["his criticism of British rule through the Lagos Daily News","his constant opposition to the expansion of the British rule","the humiliation of the British officials through his successful defense of Eleko in London","the attempt to silence British officials through the platform of the NNDP"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The London Constitutional Conference of 1957 was targeted at<\/p>","options":["increasing wider participation of the people in their Regional legislature","ensuring the speedy growth of federalism in Nigeria","imputing the voice of the people in their Independence Constitution","preparing ground works for the self-governance and inclusive development of Nigeria"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The colonial investments in extractive industries invariably led to the<\/p>","options":["urbanization of towns and cities in Nigeria","arrival of slave trading in Nigeria and Africa","motivation of a continued colonial rule","uneven development of the regions in Nigeria"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Vice President of Nigeria during the 2nd Republic was ... under the platform of the<\/p>","options":["Humphrey Nwosu, National Party of Nigeria","Alex Ekwueme, National Party of Nigeria","Adisa Akinloye, Unity Party of Nigeria","Tafawa Balewa, National Party of the Nigerians and the Cameroon"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The end of the Era of Princes in Ethiopia was a key factor in<\/p>","options":["decentralising state power in the hands of Provincial heads","centralising power in the hands of the Emperors of Ethiopia","the conquest of Southern Ethiopia","motivating the Italo-Egyptian invasion of Ethiopia"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The division of the Sokoto Caliphate into Emirates was largely due to<\/p>","options":["the autocratic directive of Dan Fodio","the rivalry that persisted between the Hausa Jihadists and the Fulani scholars","geographical reasons","economical factors"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Decree ... was the Unitarism Policy of the Major General Aguiyi Ironsi<\/p>","options":["No 34 of 1966","No 35 of 1967","No 36 of 1966","No 37 of 1967"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>All but one of the following triggered the Mahdiyya Movement in Sudan<\/p>","options":["the foreign government's growing reliance on European Christians","the Sudanese of governmental efforts to suppress the lucrative slave trade","unpleasant immigration policy of the foreign government","heavy taxation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>One important characteristic of both recent and earlier Islamic reform movements is the emphasis on the<\/p>","options":["mediation of others for understanding the Koran and traditions of the prophet","use of African languages as a medium of communication","decline in the use of educational resource institutes","rigidity of the use of Arabic language"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>All the following except one were the motivating reasons behind the Great Trek<\/p>","options":["the fear that the emigration might lead to a decline of civilisation","insecurity about the conflict on the Eastern frontier of South Africa","restoration of economic, cultural and political unity independent of the British power","threat of liberalism by the new colonial regime"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The central agenda of the Muhammad Ali&#39;s hegemonic rule was the<\/p>","options":["enslavement of the Sudanese","the exploitation of natural resources for development finance in Egypt","annexation of Sudan as an Ottoman-Egyptian Colony","political conquest of Sudan"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The most remarkable acheivement of the Buhari&#39;s Military regime is the<\/p>","options":["War Against Intolerance","Green Revolution Programme","War Against Indiscipline","Structural Adjustment Programme"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>One of the following persons was not arrested over the May Day riots<\/p>","options":["Arisekola Alao","Comrade Ola Oni","Chief Bola Ige","Lam Adesina"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Imperialist powers in Africa inbuilt antagonism by taking advantage of the cultural diversity of the people through the...<\/p>","options":["Policy of Assimilation","Divide-and-Rule Policy","Indignant Policy","Policy of Association"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>... was the only significant imperial power in the Northern half of Africa at the end of the 18th century<\/p>","options":["Ottoman Turkey","Italo-Egyptian Empire","Ottoman-Egyptian","Portuguese Empire"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The concern of Mary Slessor was primarily with<\/p>","options":["expanding the spread of colonialism under the pretext of christian missionary activities","eliminating the tribal superstitious practice of killing of triplets only","introducing the people to European culture and religion","eliminating the tribal superstitious practice of killing of twin babies"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The inception of state creation in the Nigerian military era is traceable to the regime of<\/p>","options":["Aguiyi Ironsi","Murtala\/Obasanjo","Yakubu Gowon","Ibrahim Babangida"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Early centres of civilization in Nigeria reveal the history of<\/p>","options":["descendants of the notable tribes and culture","scientific and technological developments","slave trading and colonialism","precolonial societies"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>All but one of the following played vital roles in the expansion of the missionary movements into Africa<\/p>","options":["the regeneration of the African people","the anti-slavery agenda","humanitarian conscience for Africa","the prevalence of western education"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The .... was the programme initiated to institutionalise the local government system in Nigeria<\/p>","options":["Local Government Reform of 1976","Local Government Reform of 1979","Municipal Local Authority Reform of 1976","Municipal Local Authority Reform of 1979"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>One critical factor that led to the Mfecane was the<\/p>","options":["ageing population in Southern Africa","war-created refugee problems","apartheid regime in South Africa","decline in the growth of civilization"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Centenary Anniversary of Nigeria was done to commemorate Nigeria&#39;s<\/p>","options":["Independence ceremony of October 1st 1960","Amalgamation of January 1st 1914","Republican Achievements of May 29th 1999","Amalgamation of February 1st, 1914"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Presently, about 65% of Africa&#39;s population is constituted by the<\/p>","options":["youths","age","teenagers","retired uniformed men"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The first African female President of the United Nations General Assembly is<\/p>","options":["Elizabeth Rhoda","Angie Brooks","Queen Nziga","Sirleaf Johnson"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>All except one of the following motivated the scramble for Africa<\/p>","options":["the justification that the Western Powers have the responsibilities to civilise the Non-Western Countries","an avenue for em-broadening foreign relations with Africa","the need to boost the Western Economies","that the colonies would gain access to superior European goods and influence"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Nigerian Civil war ...<\/p>","options":["lasted from 5th July, 1967 - 12th January, 1970","was fought in actual essence to reintegrate and reunify Nigeria","became inevitable because the Igbo felt that Nigeria may sooner or later divide","lasted from 7th July, 1967 - 14th January, 1970"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>King Jaja of Opobo was forcibly removed for ...<\/p>","options":["conspiracy against the British colonialists","his obstruction of commerce","the attempt to declare the freedom of his people from colonial rule","his resistance to slave trading"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The head of the administration of the Protectorate of Northern Nigeria was titled<\/p>","options":["High Commissioner","Governor-General","Lieutenant General","Emir"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>An inquiry into the need for a People-led and informed Constitution was central to ... regime<\/p>","options":["Lyttleton's","Clifford's","Richard's","Macpherson's"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>All the following except one spurred the nationalist drives in British West Africa<\/p>","options":["the existence of diverse political parties","the adoption of the policy of Assimilation","the tolerance of nationalist newspapers","unfair socio-political environment"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Lyttleton Constitution is often remarkable for all the following reasons except<\/p>","options":["the introduction of a federal structure for Nigeria","the grant of real legislative powers to the regional legislature","recognition of the need to appoint Premiers in the regions","the establishment of a public service commission"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Colonialism is often regarded as a double-edged sword particularly because<\/p>","options":["the infrastructure built from West African forced labour was also designed to exploit their natural resources","educational institutions were built which contributed to human capacity development","the raods built by the Europeans lead to the urbanization of West African towns and cities","the European investment in the extractive industry developed trade and commerce"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Nigerian Second Republic adopted a\/an ... system of governance<\/p>","options":["West-Minster","British-styled Presidential","American-styled Presidential","Confederal"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The repeated attempts by Egypt and Italy to colonize Ethiopia led to the<\/p>","options":["end of the Era of Princes in Ethiopia","conquest of Southern Ethiopia","expansion of the colonial tendencies to pacify Ethiopia","battle of Adwa"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Historically, the Yorubas came into prominence as a result of<\/p>","options":["their artworks and sculptures made to honour the gods","the impact of their language and cultural aspects","the settlement of the British colony in 1901","their trading in guns with the Portugese"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Oba Ewuare of Benin Kingdom is credited with having<\/p>","options":["successfully opposed British imperialism","successfully managed monopoly over trade which the British found irksome","succeeded Ovonramwen","transformed Benin city into a city-state"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Royal Niger Company was influential in the formation of Colonial Nigeria because it<\/p>","options":["enabled the British Empire to establish control over and above its German competitor","paved way for the emergence of the National African Company","served as a means of economic development and investment in Nigeria","encouraged the adoption of the Indirect Rule Policy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Which one of the following is incorrect?<\/p>","options":["Sarkin Fada was the head of Palace workers in the Hausa\/Fulani Empire","The Ajeles properly governed the districts in the Old Oyo Empire","The Alkali Courts were headed by the Hakimis in the Hausa\/Fulani Empire","The Igbo precolonial era was acephalous in nature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Under the chairmanship of ... the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) was formed<\/p>","options":["Yakubu Gowon","Chief Olusegun Obasanjo","Murtala Muhammed","Aguiyi Ironsi"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Unarguably, the abolition of the slave trade in Britain directly stimulated the<\/p>","options":["penetration of European merchants capital into Nigeria","spread of missionary activities into Nigeria","growth of nationalist movements in Nigeria","pace of the amalgamation of Nigeria"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The connections between Kano and the province of Nupe was notable in the reign of Kano&#39;s<\/p>","options":["Sarkin Dauda","Sarkin Ruwa","Sarkin Fada","Sarkin Yandoka"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>In 17th Century, the Dutch settlers largely relied on ... to build up South Africa<\/p>","options":["natural resources","government proceeds","black South African slaves","basic social infrastructures"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>A Policy central to the Kanem-Borno Empire was that of<\/p>","options":["the British hegemony","imperial expansion and firearms trading","nomadic orientation of its people","state-led land reforms"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>All the following except one led to the re-emergence of old trade patterns under Omani rule<\/p>","options":["availability of capital from India","increased demand for slaves","attack on the Portuguese in the 1640s","willingness of Africans in the interior to take slaves to the coast"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>In Sierra Leone, the ... was the first established Christian Church for British freed slaves among others<\/p>","options":["Methodists","Roman Catholics","Church Missionary Society","Anglican Church"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>One critical factor which spurred the abrupt termination of the Nigerian fledging democracy in the First Republic was the<\/p>","options":["nationwide corruption by the politicians","urge for sectional military representation in government","issue of tribalism and nepotism","use of the soldiers to quell civil unrests and riots"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Mahdiyya Movement in Sudan overthrew the ...<\/p>","options":["Italo-Egyptian Regime in the early 1880s","Italo-Egyptian Regime in the early 1890s","Ottoman-Egyptian Regime in the early 1880s","Ottoman-Egyptian Regime in the early 1890s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>... has primarily led to the growth of Islamic reform movements in many sub-Saharan African countries<\/p>","options":["The crisis of modernisation of the 20th Century","The new discoveries on the inadequacies of Islam","The shift in the belief and religious system of Islam","The rigidity in the use of Arabic language"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>One of the following is attributable to the Great Trek<\/p>","options":["the expansion of white communities in South Africa","the agitation for black-white equality in South Africa","the annexation of white communities by the Africans","restriction of movement of the whites in South Africa"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Khedive Ismail appointed British officers in Sudan in order to<\/p>","options":["obtain recognition for his government","introduce heavy taxation","rebuild the Sudanese territories","fight against lucrative slave trade"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The ... headed under the Chairmanship Muhammadu Buhari was the governing body in Nigeria<\/p>","options":["Armed Forces Ruling Council","Supreme Military Council","Provisional Ruling Council","Transitional Military Council"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The National Democratic Coalition (NADECO) was formed<\/p>","options":["in 1993, to press for the re-validation of the June 12, 1993 Presidential election","in 1994, to solicit funds in preparation for the transition into Civilian rule","in 1994, to press for the re-validation of the June 12, 1993 Presidential election","in 1993, to advocate for the violation of human rights under the Abacha's regime"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>All the following except one are the communes of the colony of Senegal where the Policy of Assimilation was applied<\/p>","options":["Saint Louis","Rufisque","Goree","Kaolack"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The system of imperial military rule had its deepest roots in ...<\/p>","options":["Ethiopia","Egypt","Sierra Leone","Gambia"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Traditionally, the Efik people have accounts of their migration from the territory<\/p>","options":["Igbo and Nupe","Ibibio and Igbo","Uruan and Ibibio","Biase and Annang"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Regionalism notable with ... may be said to have laid the foundational basis for the latter state creation in Nigeria<\/p>","options":["Authur Richard","John Macpherson","Oliver Lyttleton","Hugh Clifford"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Ife Civilization is most remarkable for its<\/p>","options":["use of terra cotta and bronze heads","multiplicity of idols and gods","its discovery of terra cotta (burnt clay)","use of carved woods and ivory"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>Baptists, Methodists and the ... were among the first to engage in the Liberiian Christian Mission<\/p>","options":["Presbyterian Church","United Church of Christ","Catholic Christian Mission","Episcopal Church"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Swazi composite is the modern ...<\/p>","options":["Swaziland","Southern Zibabwe","Zulu Kingdom","Southeastern Botswana"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>One of the following is not credited with the General Obasanjo&#39;s military regime<\/p>","options":["the Universal Primary Education Program","the Operation Feed the Nation","the Festival of Arts and Culture","the Structural Adjustment Programme"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"<p>The Colony and Protectorate of Nigeria was the resultant merger of the<\/p>","options":["Colony of Lagos and the Southern Protectorate","Colony and Protectorate of Southern Nigeria and the Northern Protectorate","Northern Protectorate and the Colony of Western Nigeria","Colony of Western Nigeria and the Protectorate of Southern and Northern Nigeria"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2019"},{"question":"The Nok civilization suggests that","options":["Nigeria passed through different stages of development","civilization in the area began with the Stone Age","the people of Nigeria came from the East","Nigerian civilization is related to that of Greek."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The development of mircoliths is associated with the","options":["Middle Age Stone","Late Stone Age","Iron Age","Early Stone Age."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"In pre-colonial Nigeria, intergroup contacts were encourage mostly by","options":["economic interdependence","military alliance","marriage ties","political ties"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following is the most important source of the history of the Hausa states?","options":["Tarikh-as Sudan.","The European account.","The Kano Chronicle.","The Arab traders\u2019 account."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Yoruba background to the Oba of Benin is emphasized by the","options":["similarities of Benin and Ife arts","similarities in their political structures","relationship between Oranmiyan and Ogiso dynasties","Oranmiyan legend in Benin history."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"European traders did not venture into the interior of Nigeria before the 19th century because","options":["they were ignorant of the area","the African middlemen served their needs","of their fear of the African middlemen","they were very few in number."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Africans transported across the Atlantic as slaves were mostly","options":["people with criminal records","able-bodied men","disabled persons","people with low income."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The jihadists emerged victorious in Gobir because","options":["their cause was just","the Hausa rulers were divided","they had superior weapons","the masses supported them."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Rabeh\u2019s greatest challenge after conquering Borno was","options":["normalizing relations with Sokoto Caliphate","rebuilding the armed forces","reviving the ailing economy","safeguarding the religion of Islam."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Christianity spread fast in Nigeria because it","options":["was associated with Western education","had superior spiritual appeal","preached social equality","was opposed to oppression by rulers."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Ibadan-Ijebu relations in the 19th Century became hostile as a result of","options":["boundary disputes between them","succession to the Ijebu throne","British annexation of Lagos","Ibadan\u2019s attempt to reach the coast."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Ekiti Parapo was aimed at","options":["checking European inroad into Yorubaland","restoring the dignity of the Alaafin","reducing the powers of Ibadan","forming a federated government."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Uzama title holders in Benin Kingdom were responsible for","options":["advising the Oba in the administration of the Kingdom","punishing erring members of the royal family","defending the Kingdom from external attacks","settling disputes between the Oba and other chiefs."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Britain suppressed the trans-Atlantic slave trade because","options":["there was no more market for slaves in America","it had become very inhuman","the Christian missions preached against it","it became unfavourable to her industrial progress."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The main goal of the British expedition against the Aro was to","options":["destroy the Ibini-Ukpabi oracle","eliminate all opposition to their presence in the hinterland","pave the way for the Christianization of Igboland","liberate the Igbo from Aro bondage."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A major reason for the introduction of indirect rule in Northern Nigeria was to","options":["ensure perfect control of the economy","further weaken the position of the elite class","assist the Christian missionaries in their activities","secure cheap labour for railway construction."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Nationalist activities developed earlier in British West Africa than in French West Africa because","options":["British colonies were accorded equal status with Britain","Britain had more colonies than France","African chiefs in French colonies were highly respected","of the systems of administration adopted by the colonial powers."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The main reason for the construction of the railway from Port-Harcourt into the hinterland was the","options":["discovery of tin in Jos area","discovery of a deep sea harbor at Port-Harcourt","discovery of coal at Udi","need to evacuate export crops from the hinterland."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"During the colonial period, agricultural policy in Nigeria was designed to","options":["raise the financial base of the country","make the economy compete favourably in the world market","provide raw materials for British industries","demonstrate Britain\u2019s concern for the development of its colonies."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Nigerian Youth Movement collapsed as a result of","options":["its failure to win elections","shortage of funds to run its affairs","the harassment of its leadership by government","the break-up of its leadership."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The NCNC London Delegate pressed for","options":["free primary education for all Nigerian children","autonomy for the regions","a revision of the Richards Constitution","outright independence for Nigeria."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Lyttlelton Constitution is considered a landmark in the history of Nigeria, because it","options":["created a federal structure of government for the country","made ministers accountable to the electorate","recognized Lagos as a federal territory","gave ministers full authority over their ministries."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Protests by trade unions in Nigeria during the colonial period were aimed at","options":["achieving political independence","establishing more industries","obtaining specific benefits for members","fighting corruption among government officials."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following served as federal ministers under the Tafawa Balewa Administration?","options":["Alhaji Muhammadu Ribadu and Chief Festus Okotie-Eboh.","Chief Kolawole Balogun and Alhaji Adamu Ciroma.","Alhaji Muhammadu Inuwa Wada and Chief Richard Akinjide","Chief Aja Nwachukwu and Alhaji Umaru Dikko."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An important function of FEDECO during the 1979 elections was","options":["establishing party offices","promulgating the new constitution into law","swearing-in of elected officials","delineating electoral constituencies."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A major reason for the military intervention in Nigeria\u2019s politics in 129966 was the","options":["pro-West posture of Nigeria\u2019s foreign policy","over-bearing power of traditional rulers","attempt by government to retire top military officers","crisis of the 1964 General Elections."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Major General Aguiyi-Ironsi introduced a unitary system of government because","options":["it was the wish of the people","of the command structure of the military","he wanted more revenue for the central government","other military officers were planning to overthrow him."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The strategy for accelerated agricultural development of the Obasanjo regime in the 1970\u2019s focused on","options":["improving transportation network to the rural areas","establishing agro-allied industries","achieving food self-sufficiency","establishing new marketing boards."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Berber scholar, al-Mukhtar, contributed to the success of the Masina Jihad by","options":["fighting alongside Seju Ahmadu","preparing the ground through the Qadiriyyah Brotherhood","mobilizing various groups to fight for Seku Ahmadu","appealing to Ardo Moudo to support Seku Ahmadu."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The establishment of Freetown in 1822 facilitated","options":["the settlement of freed slaves","Christian missionary activities","humanitarian activities","the improvement of agriculture."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Nineteenth century Egyptian nationalism principally aimed at","options":["controlling the Suez Canal","forming a constitutional government in Egypt","bringing down the monarchy","ensuring Egyptian independence."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Battle of Tel el-Kebir was fought between","options":["the British and the Urabists","Tawfiq and the Mahdists","the Khedive and the Wafdists","Napoleon and the Mamluks."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Morocco was of strategic importance to the European countries because","options":["of its good climatic conditions","it was highly industrialized","it possessed good mineral resources","it provided an entrance to the Mediterranean."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Mahdists revolt in the Sudan was successful","options":["They believed they had a superior faith","it enjoyed widespread support","the Egyptian army was poorly trained","General Gordon was an incompetent commander."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Sayyid Said increased the volume of trade with the Europeans by","options":["allowing them to take control of the trade with the hinterland","replacing Indian middlemen with Europeans","allowing European consuls to reside in Zanzibar","making English the lingua franca of Zanzibar."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"One of the main aims of the British conquest of Buganda was to","options":["gain access to the cape of Good Hope","pain control of the gold mines of Bunyoro","prevent other Europeans from controlling the source of the Nile","take control of the trade routes in the area."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The survival of Ethiopia as an independent polity was as a result of the","options":["location of the kingdom","alliance with some European powers","strong economic base of the kingdom","introduction of a compulsory military service."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The Mfecane resulted in the","options":["division and fragmentation of the Zulu nation","formation of the Ndebele state","decrease in Boer influence in South Africa","dispersal of the Zulu to the Katanga copper belt."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The 1960 Sharpeville revolt was specifically against","options":["labour laws","land laws","pass laws","marriage laws."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A major consequence of the Great Trek was the","options":["restriction of movement of the whites in South Africa","agitation for black-white equality in South Africa","annexation of white communities by the Africans","the expansion of white communities in South Africa."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"One feature of European diplomacy in the scramble for Africa was","options":["exchanging of ambassadors among them","holding Africans hostage for negotiations","negotiating with African leaders for territories","reconciling differences over territorial claims."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The French colonial policy of assimilation failed in Africa because","options":["African culture was deeply rooted","the African elite were opposed to it","it was not consistently implemented","it was expensive to implement."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following was one of the demands of the National Congress of British West Africa?","options":["Establishment of a university in each of the colonies.","Expulsion of all Syrians and Lebanese from the colonies.","Election of Africans into each colony\u2019s council.","Restriction of the activities of Christian missionaries in the colonies."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The nationalist movement in Nigeria during the post-war period was primarily led by","options":["businessmen","the intelligentsia","students","local chiefs."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"One of the objectives for the formation of the South African Native Congress in 1912 was to","options":["establish a political party","encourage black participation in governance","retrieve all lands seized by the whites","integrate the various groups and races."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"In 1973, Nigeria broke diplomatic relations with Israel because of Israel\u2019s","options":["occupation of Egyptian territory","support for apartheid South Africa","support for Biafra during the war","raid on Entebbe airport in Uganda."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"King Leopold\u2019s colonial ventures in the Congo were aimed at","options":["making Belgium a great colonial power","carving out an empire for himself","putting a stop to domestic slave trade in the area","introducing Western education to the people."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"In Africa, the colonial authorities introduced modern means of transportation in order to","options":["develop the internal markets","increase farmers\u2019 purchasing power","encourage urban development","promote import-export trade."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The savannah region of Nigeria is<br>\r\ncharacterized by","options":["sparse vegetation","high population density","abundant resources","large bodies of water."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A major economic activity among the Nupe was","options":["horse breeding","leather work","canoe-building","cattle rearing."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The main features of the economy of the forest zone of Nigeria in the eighteenth century were","options":["pastoral farming and fishing","fishing and salt-making","cotton cultivation and weaving","cash crop production and trading."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The spread of Islam between the 11th and 14th centuries in Nigeria was largely due to","options":["Arab missionary activities","the waging of jihads","trade and commerce","absence of any religion in the area."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A significant effect of the Christian missionary activity in Nigeria was the","options":["introduction of formal education","training of nationalists","introduction of new crops","abolition of the slave trade."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"An outstanding reason for the abolition of the trans-Atlantic slave trade was","options":["industrial revolution","nationalist agitation","legitimate trade","railway construction."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A major factor that led to the success of the Sokoto jihad was","options":["military assistance from Borno","lack of unity among the Hausa states","the use of fire-arms by the jihadists","periodic divine interventions."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following was a part of the Sokoto Caliphate?","options":["Kukawa.","Yauri.","Biu.","Lokoja."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The legendary founder of the Kanuri was","options":["Ali Ghaji","Idris b. Ali Katagarmabe","Idris Alooma","Sayf b. dhi Yazan."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Queen mother, Magira, played a prominent role in the government of the","options":["Hausa States","Kwararafa Kingdom","Kanem Borno Empire","Igala Kingdom."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Ekiti Parapo was an alliance against","options":["the Muslim incursion into Yorubaland","the rising power of Ibadan","Christian missionary presence in Yorubaland","the abolition of the slave trade."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Oyo Empire collapsed as a result of","options":["internal and external crises","the revolt of Afonja","the weakening of the army","British presence in Yorubaland."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The failure of the Ogiso dynasty in Benin was attributed to","options":["weakness and dependence of the rulers","peoples\u2019 resentment against the system","the declining economy of the state","inadequate supply of arms and ammunition."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The greatest ruler in the history of Benin Kingdom was","options":["Oba Ewuare","Oba Ewedo","Oba Ovonramwen","Oba Ewuakpe."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Armed resistance to British rule in Northern Nigeria ended with the conquest of","options":["Kano and Sokoto","Bida and Kano","Katsina and Kano","Bauchi and Katsina."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Colony and Protectorate of Lagos was amalgameted with the Protectorate of Southern Nigeria in 1906 to form the","options":["Colony and Protectorate of Southern Nigeria","Colony and Protectorate of Nigeria","Protectorate of Southern Nigeria","Oil Rivers Protectorate."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A reason for the amalgamation of the Northern and Southern protectorates of Nigeria in 1914 was","options":["economic expediency","territorial integration","political balancing","religious harmony."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Nigerian Council established in 1914 was ineffective because it","options":["was not designed to be so","lacked sufficient funds","had too many vocal members","was dominated by hand-picked members."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Two institutions of local government in Nigeria during the colonial period were native courts and","options":["legislative council","regional treasury","native treasury","native police."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Certain chiefs in Eastern Nigeria were called warrant chiefs because they","options":["had some royal connections","were created by the British","had warrants to arrest offenders","were the first to receive Western education."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In colonial Nigeria, mining industry was promoted in order to","options":["diversify the economy","engage the railway system","make Nigeria self-reliant","maximize exploitation."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The colonial government in Nigeria laid more emphasis on the production of export crops because","options":["the people already had abundant food in stock","such crops were desperately needed abroad","such crops were more beneficial to the people","the soil was more suitable for the production of such crops."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Yaba Higher College did not meet the aspirations of the nationalists because","options":["all its staff were Europeans","it was meant to train assistants to Europeans","only Europeans were qualified for admission","it was affiliated to a polytechnic in Europe."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The 1922 Clifford Constitution restricted the franchise to","options":["Calabar and Benin","Lagos and Calabar","Lagos and Warri","Warri and Lokoja"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The political parties that formed the opposition during the First Republic in Nigeria were the","options":["NCNC and AG","AG and UMBC","NCNC and NEPU","UMBC and NEPU."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The creation of Mid-Western region in 1963 was through","options":["balloting","referendum","declaration","voting."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The immediate cause of the January 1966 coup d\u2019etat was","options":["the breakdown of law and order in the West","the desire of the military to seize power","the failure of the 1963 census","interferance by foreign powers"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following countries did the Murtala\/Obasanjo regime assist during their struggle for independence?","options":["Guinea Bissau and Namibia","Angola and Zimbabwe","Sierra Leone and Equitorial Guinea.","The Gambia and Tanzania"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Second Republic in Nigeria refers to<br>\r\nthe period","options":["General Babangida was Head of State","between 1979 and 1983","General Obasanjo was Head of State","the period between 1960 and 1966"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following political parties<br>\r\nformed an alliance in the Second<br>\r\nRepublic?","options":["UPN and NPN.","PRP and NPP.","NPN and NPP.","PRP and UPN."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The political party that controlled the Federal Government during the Second Republic in Nigeria was the","options":["Great Nigeria Peoples Party","Nigeria Peoples Party","Unity Party of Nigeria","National Party of Nigeria."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The main aim of the formation of ECOMOG was to","options":["foster stability in West Africa","solve boundary disputes among member states","provide security for the whole of Africa","tackle the problem of piracy in African seaways."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A major contribution of Nigeria to<br>\r\nECOWAS is in the area of","options":["diplomacy","funding","military support","provision of education."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Samori Toure is often described as the \u201cAfrican Napoleon\u201d because he","options":["was a great military tactician","learned a great deal from Napoleon","employed similar tactics as Napoleon","had a well trained army."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A major similarity of the 19th century jihads in West Africa was that","options":["they were executed at the same time","the participants were of the same origin","they had a common objective","they brought unity between the Hausa and the Fulani."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The greatest contribution of the Christian Missionary Society in West Africa was in","options":["establishing trading companies","stopping the slave trade","the emergence of educated elite","the production of cash crop."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Egypt became the centre of international rivalry because of the","options":["huge investment in the Suez-canal","rich soil for cotton and sugar cultivation","great cities of Cairo and Alexandria","strategic importance of the country."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Muhammad es Sadek was a 19th century ruler of","options":["Morocco","Libya","Tunisia","Algeria."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Muhammad Ahmad was easily accepted as the Mahdi in the Sudan because","options":["the Islamic leaders in the area did not live up to the expectations of the people","he came at a time the people were expecting to be delivered from the Egyptian rulers","the national army was not strong enough to defend the country","he was highly educated in the tenants of the Islamic religion."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"After leaving Oman for East Africa, Sayyid Said established his headquarters in","options":["Zanzibar","Pemba","Mombasa","Kilwa."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In 1887, a plot to depose Kabaka Mwanga was hatched by","options":["a Muslim group","Baganda Christians","Arab slave merchants","Egyptian mercenaries."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"An Ethiopian monarch that committed suicide in a battle field was","options":["Theodore II","Menelik","Johannes IV","Haile Selassie."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The white settlers in Southern Africa were known as","options":["Bantu","Boers","Bushmen","Hottentots."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Mfecane occured as a result of","options":["long standing inter-group rivalry","inter-group struggles for natural resources","Ndwandwe\u2019s domination of the Zulu","Shaka\u2019s inordinate military ambition."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Fashoda incident of 1898 resulted in a rift between","options":["France and Germany","Germany and Britain","France and Italy","Britain and France."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Paternalism was a colonial policy adopted<br>\r\nby","options":["Britain","Portugal","Germany","France."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Where was indirect rule practised before it was introduced to Africa?","options":["India.","Malaysia.","Pakistan.","Indonesia."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The indirect rule system of administration meant that the colonialists","options":["ruled through native courts","barred the educated elite from local politics","ruled through traditional institutions","relied mostly on local interpreters"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In post-apartheid South Africa, the main concern of government is to","options":["punish the people who perpetrated apartheid","redress the injustices of the apartheid policy","make the country the giant of Africa","make the country a permanent member of the UN Security Council"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The Ogaden war between Ethiopia and Somalia was caused by","options":["disagreement over trade","refugee problems","boundary disputes","personality clash between their leaders"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In the Ekine society of the Niger Delta, promotion was based on","options":["artistic ability","the number of slaves possessed","respect for age","personal conduct."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following groups belongs to the Jos Plateau?","options":["Gbagyi and Nupe","Idoma and Igede","Berom and Angas","Jukun and Tiv."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The emergence of states in Hausaland was mainly attributed to","options":["trading activities","wars of conquest","immigration of groups","population increase."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In the 18th century, Zaria was under the<br>\r\ninfluence of","options":["Sokoro","Daura","Kano","Borno."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Islam was introduced in Kano during the reign of","options":["Sarkin Kano Ibrahim Dabo","Sarkin Kano Kanajeji","Sarkin Kano Muhammadu Rumfa","Sarkin Kano Yaji."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A major cause of depopulation in Nigeria in the 18th century was","options":["the trans-Atlantic slave trade","the trans-Saharan trade","human sacrifice","inter-ethnic warfare."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The Sokoto Jihad was","options":["the first Islamic movement in West Africa","an attempt to establish Fulani dominance","the last of the 19th century Jihads","the origin of the other Jihads in West Africa."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The women who wielded political influence in Borno were","options":["Magara, Magira and Gumsu","Gumsu, Daurama and Magira","Turunku, Magara and Gumsu","Daurama, Turunku and Kaugama"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following pionnered Christian missionary activities in Calabar?","options":["Mary Slessor","William Baike","Thomas Freeman","Hope Waddell."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A factor responsible for the growth of large towns among the Yoruba was the","options":["absence of conflict in the area","concentration of Europeans in the area","fertile nature of the soil in the area","high centralization of authority in the area."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The greatest problem faced by the Old Oyo Empire in the early 19th century was the","options":["weakening of the central authority","incursion of the jihadists","British encroachment into Yorubaland","dominant influence of Bashorun Gaha."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The main cause of the decline of the Benin Kingdom in the 19th century was the","options":["absence of a strong and effective army","bitter struggle for the throne by the ruling families","strained relations between Benin and Agbor","British abolition of the trans- Atlantic slave trade."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The Egba welcomed the British missionaries in the 19th century because","options":["they wanted British protection","of their desire to accept Christianity","of their quest for Western education","they wanted to established trade with the British."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"One of the early Nigerian leaders who collaborated with British and later resisted was","options":["King Jaja of Opobo","Nana of Itsekiri","sultan Attahiru","king Dappa Williams."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The Royal Niger Company was renamed","options":["British West African Company","United African Company","Lever Brothers NigeriaPlc","Leventis Nigeria Plc."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The British policy of indirect rule sought to","options":["encourage the educated elite to participate in local administration","make the indigenous political institutions adapt to British system of Government","use indigenous political institutions to serve British interest","promote co-operation between the educated elite and the indigenous rulers.."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The principal target of the Aba Women demonstrators of 1929 were the","options":["Warrant chiefs","European traders","Christian missionaries","Court clerks."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following were former British colonies?","options":["Nigeria, Ghana, Gambia and Liberia","Cameroon, Togo, Egypt and Ghana","Sierra Leone, Gambia, Nigeria and Ghana","Nigeria, Ghana, Senegal and South Africa"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Transportation network in colonial Nigeria was established to","options":["ease local transportation problem of women","encourage visits among distant relations","support the movement of raw materials and the army","provide employment for the people"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In colonial Nigeria, export crop production was dominated by","options":["the Europeans","the Labanese","peasant farmers","indigenous middlemen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Sabon Gari settlement in most parts of colonial Nigeria harboured mostly","options":["people other than the indigenes","indigenes who were Muslims","strangers who were Muslims only","European traders and missionaries"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The Richards Constitution of 1946 brought about","options":["decolonization","independence","a strong central government","regional politics."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The Native Authority system in Northern Nigerian was established to","options":["assist in the collection of taxes and general administration","regulate the number of European District Officers","streamline electoral laws in the area","support the spread of Christian missionary activities."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Anti-colonial movements Nigeria before the World War II involved","options":["attempts to violently chase the British out of the country","collaboration with the British authority","peaceful protests through petitions and conferences","the establishment of pressure groups by traditional rulers."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Politics in Nigeria\u2019s First republic was characterized by","options":["religion and ethnicity","religion and regionalism","ethnicity and regionalism","regionalism and despotism."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In 1963, the Eastern region of Nigeria went to the supreme court over the","options":["decision of the federal government to conduct a fresh census","exclusion of Easterners resident in the North from the census","the population figures of the national census","exclusion of women in the national census."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The immediate cause of the Nigerian Civil War was the","options":["coup detat of January 1966","crisis in the Western region","poor social policy of the First Republic","crisis of the 1962 Census"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The major reason for Nigeria\u2019s interest in the Liberian Civil War was to save herself from","options":["bearing the burden of the war\u2019s refugees","losing her investments in Liberia","losing her citizens in Liberia","losing her position as a regional power."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The most significant act of statesmanship associated with<br>\r\nAbdulsalami regime was","options":["promulgate the 1999 Constitution","handing over power to a civilian government","the release of political prisoners","organizing successful general elections."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The major feature of the War against Indiscipline were","options":["queuing culture and environmental sanitation","public flogging and payment of fines","arrest of offenders and imprisonment of convicts","high slogans and beating of drums."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following was referred to as \u2018Province of Freedom\u2019 in the 19th century?","options":["Liberia","Ghana","The Gambia","Sierra Leone."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The early missionaries abandoned their work in Benin mainly because of","options":["antagonism from the Oba","resistance from the people","lack of resources","ill health and health."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In 1805, Muhammad Ali became the Pasha of Egypt as a result of","options":["his leadership qualities","the deposition of the sultan","his military background","the voluntary retirement of the sultan."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"French delay in occupying Algeria was attributed to","options":["demographic reasons","insufficient officials","the people\u2019s resistance","fear of British reaction."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The Mahdiyya Movement in the sudan was principally a reaction against","options":["internal oppression","northern domination","foreign pressures","economic difficulties."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The reign of Sayyid said in East Africa was marked by","options":["a gradual growth in Portuguese influence","decline in the slave trade","crises at home and pirates at sea","the loss of Pate to the Mazrui."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"By 1700, the Portuguese had been expelled from all their coastal strongholds in East Africa by the","options":["Arab traders","English traders","Belgium traders","Indian traders."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"One of the factors that attracted the Europeans to East Africa was the desire","options":["for tropical produce","for territorial expansion","to establish Christian missions","to spread Western education."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The rise of Shaka the Zulu was a result<br>\r\nof the","options":["introduction of new military tactics","support he got from the Boer","wealth he acquired from heavy taxation","decentralization of political authority."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The dissatisfaction of the Boer with<br>\r\nBritish reforms at the Cape Colony<br>\r\nmade them to","options":["stage a rebellion against the British","negotiate peace settlement with the British","form a strong political organization","emigrate from the area."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The policy of separation of the races in South Africa was first adopted in the Cape by the","options":["British","French","Germans","Boer."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The last European power to join the race for colonies in Africa was","options":["France","Portugal","Germany","Belgium."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The area later referred to as Cameroon was mandated to","options":["France and Britain","Portugal and Spain","Belgium and Italy","Germany and Belgium."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The British government took over the control of the Colony of Sierra Leone in 1807 in order to use it as a","options":["major trading port in the West African region","centre for the spread of British culture","base for anti-slave trade naval patrol","base to penet West African interior."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Nationalist\u2019s resistance to colonialism in Africa was influenced by","options":["the level of literacy among the people","relations between the Africans and Europeans","the effect of Islamic religion on the people","the nature and character of the leadership."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The nationalist leaders who played prominent roles during Zimbabwe\u2019s struggle for independence were","options":["Robert Mugabe and Joshua Nkomo","Abel Muzerewaand Kamuzu Banda","Sam Nujoma and Chris Hani","Ndabaningi Sithole and Augustiho Neto."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The principal anti-apartheid party in South Africa was the","options":["African National Congress","Afrikaner National Party","National Party","Unionist Congress."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The power that emerged after the First World War was","options":["Great Britain","Russia","the USA","Japan."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Northern Rhodesia, on becoming a Crown Colony, was administered by the","options":["United Nations Organization","Commonwealth of Nations","British Foreign Affairs Department","British Colonial Office."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Islam was introduced in Kano during the reign of","options":["Sarkin Kano Ibrahim Dabo","Sarkin Kano Kanajeji","Sarkin Kano Muhammadu Rumfa","Sarkin Kano Yaji."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A major cause of depopulation in Nigeria in the 18th century was","options":["the trans-Atlantic slave trade","the trans-Saharan trade","human sacrifice","inter-ethnic warfare."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The Sokoto Jihad was","options":["the first Islamic movement in West Africa","an attempt to establish Fulani dominance","the last of the 19th century Jihads","the origin of the other Jihads in West Africa."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The women who wielded political influence in Borno were","options":["Magara, Magira and Gumsu","Gumsu, Daurama and Magira","Turunku, Magara and Gumsu","Daurama, Turunku and Kaugama."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The collapse of Kanem under Dunama Debalemi was attributed to","options":["poor economic system","lack of a standing army","conflict among the ruling class","lack of a sound political structure."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following areas did Malam Alimi incorporate into the Sokoto Caliphate?","options":["Bida","Ilorin","Adamawa","Bauchi"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The most powerful states that emerged after the fall of the Old Oyo were","options":["Owu and Abeokuta","Ijaiye and Ife","Ibadan and Ijaiye","New Oyo and Ibadan."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The ethnic groups that occupy the hinterland of the Bight of Benin include the","options":["Edo, the Yoruba and the Urhobo","Itsekiri, the Igbo and the Idoma","Yoruba, the Jukun and the Efik","Igbo, the Ibibio and the Tiv"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Nok culture is associated with the archaelogical findings at","options":["Ile-Ife","Benin","Taruga","Igbo Ukwu."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In the pre-colonial period, the Aku of Wukari derived his power mainly from","options":["the strength of his army","the role as a supplier of slaves","his control of trade routes","his spiritual influence in the kingdom."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The last ruler of the Ogiso dynasty in the Benin Empire was","options":["Oba Eweka","Oba Owodo","Oba Oranmiyan","Oba Ewuare."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Olu of Itsekiri was assisted in his administration by a council of chiefs<br>\r\ncalled","options":["Ogboni","Ekpako","Ekine","Ojoye."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In pre-colonial Nigeria, the Nsibidi form of writing was found in the","options":["Niger-Benue Confluence","Cross River Area","Niger Delta","Anambra River Valley."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Bayajidda tradition suggests that","options":["Hausa ancestors came from Arabia","women exercised political power in pre-Islamic Hausaland","the introduction of Islam led to the formation of the Hausa city states","The Queen of Daura was the first to embrace Islam."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following rulers of Kano promoted Islam to a state religion?","options":["Kanajeji","Rumfa","Yaji","Abdullahi"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The correspondence between Sokoto and Borno during the jihad was entered on the","options":["qualification for a true Muslin to perform the hajj","justification of the jihad against an Islamic state","declaration of the jihad against non-Muslims","difference between traditional religion and Islam."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The most powerful states that emerged after the fall of the Old Oyo were","options":["Owu and Abeokuta","Ijaiye and Ife","Ibadan and Ijaiye","New Oyo and Ibadan."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following areas did Malam Alimi incorporate into the Sokoto Caliphate?","options":["Bida","Ilorin","Adamawa","Bauchi"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The 1886 Treaty is significant in Yoruba history because it","options":["brought peace and stability to Yorubaland","affirmed Ekitiparapo\u2019s independence","was negotiated by two Yoruba repatriates","reopened trade between Lagos and the hinterland."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Intensified European activity along the coast in the nineteenth century led Benin to","options":["redirect her trade to the north","lose control of some vassal states","expel Christian missionaries","embark on a cultural revival in the area."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"It was difficult for the Nigerian coastal chiefs to give up the slave trade after its abolition because","options":["it had been part of African culture","Africans were too involved to give up the trade","the British Navy was not effective in enforcing the abolition","the trade was still crucial to the economy of their states."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The ruler that was driven out of Lagos by the British was","options":["Oba Akintoye","Oba Dosumu","Oba Kosoko","Oba Adele."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following played the greatest role in the British conquest of Nigeria?","options":["The John Holt Company","The Royal Niger Company","The Church Missionary Society","The Roman Catholic Mission."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Chief Agho Obaseki is remembered is Benin history because","options":["he collaborated with the British to suppress the monarchy","he was regarded as a true patriot","he played an important role in the restoration of the monarchy","Oba Aguobasimi delegated a lot of powers to him."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An influential advocate of the amalgamation of the Northern and Southern Protectorates was","options":["E.D. morel","Otunba Payne","John Beecroft","Henry Carr"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Native Authority Ordinance of 1916 introduced direct taxation into Yorubaland and thereby","options":["gave greater administrative and judicial responsibilities to the Oba","made Yorubaland a beneficiary of British aid","encouraged the appointment of more British officials","involved the educated elite in colonial administration."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The colonial officer who was responsible for splitting the Southern Province in to Eastern and Western Provinces was","options":["Bernard Bourdillon","Graeme Thompson","Hugh Clifford","Frederick Lugard."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The 1945 General Strike was led by","options":["Herbert Macaulay","Michael Imoudu","Wahab Goodluck","Olufunmilayo Ransome-Kuti."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The objective of the 1934 legislation imposing quotas on imported goods from non-British sources was to","options":["develop Nigerian industries","increase Nigeria\u2019s Gross National Product","exclude cheap Japanese textiles","regulate trade between Nigeria and other countries."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Tin Producers\u2019 Association was formed in 1929 to","options":["increase the production of tin","alleviate the hardship of miners","regulate the supply of tin","introduce modern methods of production."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"One major inadequacy of the Richards Constitution was that","options":["it was introduced without due and exhaustive consultations","the official members of the legislature were too many","it could not solve Nigeria\u2019s economic and social problems","it did not cater for the interest of the minorities."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A major recommendation of the Henry Willink Commission was the","options":["protection of special interests","creation of more administrative units","inclusion of a bill of rights in the 1960 Constitution","need to ensure the educational rights of the people."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The political party with the most radical orientation in the First Republic was the","options":["NEPU","NPC","NCNC","AG."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Premier of the Eastern Region of Nigeria in 1962 was","options":["Chief Michael Okpara","Dr. Nnamdi Azikiwe","Dr. Akanu Ibiam","Mr. Ukpabi Asika."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Nigerian National Alliance won the<br>\r\n1964 Federal Election by a landslide<br>\r\nbecause the","options":["party was popular with the masses","United Progressive Grand Alliance boycotted it","opposition parties were poorly organized","party represented the aspirations of the minority groups"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following served as a commander of the ECOMOG?","options":["Bashir Magashi","Victor Malu","Ishaya Bamaiyi","Sam Tella."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Samori Toure adopted the \u2018scorched earth\u2019 policy in his","options":["military recruitment and training","Islamic reform movement","war against the French","war against rebellious neighbours."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Sierra Leone was very important in the history of West Africa during the colonial period as a","options":["centre for the spread of Christianity","place for the spread of African culture","centre for the export of African goods","leading producer of cotton."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Mohammed Ali was able to gain effective control of Egypt","options":["by defeating the Wahabis","by eliminating the Mamluks","with the support of the Felahin","with the support of the French."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The first Magherebian state to be detached from the Ottoman Empire by the French was","options":["Tunisia","Libya","Morocco","Algeria."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Under the Qaramanli rulers, the economy of Libya depend on","options":["agriculture and slave trade","piracy and trade","taxation and tribute","war booties and tolls."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A major impact of the Omani on East Africa was the","options":["spread of Islam","emergence of states","improvement in agriculture","introduction of the slave trade."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The prime minister in the kingdom of Buganda was known as","options":["Mugema","Katikiro","Kabaka","Omuwanika."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The greatest achievement of Mutesa II in Buganda was his","options":["ability to resist European imperialism","conquest of large territories","diplomacy in dealing with foreigners","management of religious crises."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The economic reforms of Theodore II of Ethiopia involved the","options":["encouragement of slave trade","improvement of agriculture","reorganization of the fiscal system","revival of external trade."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The outbreak of the Mfecane is attributable to","options":["the tragic death of Dingiswayo","Dingiswayo\u2019s attempt to impose a European model of administration","the search for grazing and habitable land","the flight of the Swazi northwards."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The first Boer republic established as a result of the Great Trek was","options":["Transvaal","the Cape","the Orange Free State","Natal."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The European power that acquired the largest number of territories in West Africa was","options":["Britain","Germany","Belgium","France."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The French policy of assimilation failed primarily because","options":["Africans lacked the required level of education","It was expensive to implement","it required total rejection of African culture","no African sought to be assimilated."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The Mau Mau revolt in Kenya had its origin in the","options":["colonial government\u2019s inability to provide essential services to the people","imprisonment of Jomo Kenyatta by the colonial administration","occupation of Kikuyu land by the British","inherent militancy of the Kikuyu."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"One of the achievements of the National congress of British West Africa was the","options":["introduction of the elective principle","establishment of democracy","propagation of Christianity","establishment of newspapers."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Amilcar Cabral led the liberation struggle against Portuguese domination is","options":["Angola","Mozambique","Guinea Bissau","Cape Verde."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The immediate reaction of the Commonwealth to the Sharpeville massacre was the","options":["expulsion of South Africa from the organization","invitation of South Africa to a negotiation","organization of anti-apartheid conferences","declaration of an anti-apartheid year."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The leader of the South African Black consciousness Movement who died in detention in 1977 was","options":["Walter Sisulu","Albert Luthuli","Robert Sobukwe","Steve Biko."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The president Transvaal who led the Boers against the Britist was","options":["J. Smuts","P. Kruger","L. Jameson","L. Botha"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"}]